So let's learn base 16 otherwise known as
hexadecimal. So the key to it would be nice
if we could just use base 2 for everything but
zeros and ones are easy to understand but when
numbers get larger like characters for example
are eight bits it's really hard to represent that
all in base 2. So it's we we tend to see in the
real world that most machine language and other
things require you to understand hexadecimal. So,
if you take a look at base two, it was easy. We
had a simple conversion table. And I hope by now
some of you have memorized this little table. I
know I've memorized I I just, you know, when
I see seven, I see three ones. When I see six,
I see 1 1 zero. I know this by heart. Okay, now
that's cool. We're seeing all numbers that we're
familiar with. Base 16 says we are going to
represent 0 through 15 with a single digit.
Right? So 15 is 15 but with two digits. And
so the whole idea of changing bases is that we
have digits. So we need to come up with a single
digit that represents 9 10 11 12 13 14 and 15.
And so I basically said, okay, wouldn't it be cool
if we would use emojis for that? Because I have
trouble remembering hexadecimal. So if we imagine
that um 10, which is kind of zero, 11, 12, 13,
I don't they don't have an emoji for four fingers,
and then 15. So I I put a shamrock in for 14. Um,
and so, so the point here is you need a
single character to represent it. And so,
so I I made this up and then I'm like, "Hey,
AI, what emojis would you use to represent
um 10 through 15?" So, there is an actual emoji
that's 10, but there is no emoji for 11. And so,
they use the pause emoji. And then they used a
clock, 12:00, 1:00, 2:00, and 3:00. And it's not
too bad. And um American Sign Languages uses one
hand. I think I think this is 11 or maybe Yeah,
I think this is 11. Uh and so British Sign
Language is different. Uh the problem is is we
don't get emotion uh when we uh make emojis. So
we can't really use American Sign Language even
though American Sign Language has way to represent
11 12 13 and 14 and 15 uh with kind of a gesture.
So the problem was is basically whatever 1930 1940
when we started using hexadecimal we didn't have
emojis it was just too early and so all we had
was ASCII characters and so we have repurposed
A through F to represent 10 through 15 for base 16
numbers. So a is 10. The first number that is not
a single digit, right? And f is 15 and f is all
ones. Four four ones is one one one is f. Okay. So
we just used a through f. It it's a little weird
because there's the letter a and then there is
the hexadecimal digit a but you have to kind of
get used to it to say oh we're in a context of a
number here. So so that means 10. A means 10. So
if we look at the conversion between base 16 and
base 10 and I got my little cheat sheet here of 10
through 15 because 0 through nine is pretty easy.
Again base 10 says that each column is a power
of 10. So the far right column is 10 to the 0ero
which is the ones column. The the middle column is
10 to the 1 which is the 10's column. And then the
third column is 10 squared which is the hundred's
column. And so 123 is 1 * 100 2 * 10 + 3 * 1 which
is 123 b 10 which of course it is in base 16. Now
we have more digits to work with. So we have 7b
base 16. Well the far right is 16 to the 0 or
1 and then the second digit is 16 to the first
power. So the result is 7 * 16 + 11 * 1 which is
112 + 11 which is 123. Now one thing we like about
base 16 is it's easily converted to and from base
2. Um and so if you have 8 bit numbers you can
represent them with two base 16 digits. And that's
what we're going to work with a lot going forward
is eight bit numbers. So you can take and convert
like 7B b 16 which is a bite and you can convert
the seven and then you convert the b and that's
the base 2. And so to some degree hexadimal is
just a more succinct base 2 where four digits of
base 2 become one digit of base 16. If we did this
on base 10, there wouldn't be this nice lineup
because you can make really long hexadesimal
numbers and they still line up on every four-bit
boundary with base 2. So for now, keep it simple.
I tend to have to go through base 10. Um, you
know, we have a eights column now. So the top line
is 1 8 + 1 2 which is 10. 8 + 2 is 10. And that is
a base 16. uh 8 which is 1 0 0 0 is 8 base 10 and
8 base 16. So all the numbers 0 through nine are
easy. And then all ones 1 one1 is 8 + 4 + 2 + 1
which is 15. And that's f in base 16. So I've
told you that I'm pretty much a whiz at base 8,
which is three base 2 digits. I I can kind of do
that in my sleep. I am not very good at base 16.
Hopefully, you'll be better at it. Or maybe not.
So, this is my this is how I do base 16 in my head
and it's not pretty. So, F is easy because that's
15. That's the largest base 16 digit. And it's all
ones, right? That's cool. It's base 16. F is one
less. It's all ones. If you add one to it, it's
it turns into the 16 column. So an E I can do E
because I just take the all the digits and I take
off the one bit, right? So that's like 14. I can
get that. A is easy because it's like nine. What's
after nine? Oh, it's A. And so I can do that. So I
understand that's 10. And B is 11. And I was like,
uh, it's kind of like one beyond uh, A. And so I
can see what B is. I have problems with C and D,
right? I mean, I eventually have to slow down and
use my brain and go A 10, B1, C12, and then I have
to convert to base 2, which is 11 1, and then
I'm like, oh, that's A+ 4. Oh, yeah, 12. Yeah,
there you go. And D just makes me crazy, right?
I sooner or later sometimes with D, I'm like,
uh, what is it? And then I have to write it
down. So um for a good time you can go ahead
and ask AI what is a good way to do hex to base
2 conversions in your head. I did that and it
was really complex. So no so maybe I'm okay by
being confused about this. So just make yourself
a little cheat sheet whenever you have to do
hex or just get used to it or look at a table.
A lot of what we're going to do is represent
characters. And characters are asking characters
are eight bits and can really nicely and densely
be represented by two hex digits. We called these
half bytes, nibbles. Um not that it matters
much, but this asky chart shows the decimal,
the hex um octal, which we tend not to use,
and then the binary. So if you look at 42,
it's kind of small on this screen, but you see
that it's 42 decimal and 0x2A hexadimal, which is
asterisk. And so I tend to just look these things
up and I don't really convert them um and just
use hex as a way to look things up in things like
ASI tables. Now while we're speaking about ASI so
so ASI is a historical code set basically that is
very western and really goes back to Latin really
and because we have 8bit bytes um and the west
built computers early on we tended to have asy
character sets were universal across computers
but that's not real there's Asian character sets
sets and Indian character sets and Arabic and
Persian character sets. They're they're all kind
of different. And so what happened was in in the
time where computing became a worldwide activity,
we needed to come up with a way to interchange
characters that are way bigger than eight bits.
And somebody came up with the idea of Unicode. And
Unicode has all kinds of character sets, you know,
Latin and ASKI start and then they just have all
kinds of character sets. Some of these are Latin
characters with like umlouts and all things like
that. And some of them are like Asian characters
that are pictograms. Now, recently emojis are in
Unicode as well. And so some of the emojis that
I've showed you are actually have a Unicode
code. Unicode represents things by 32 bits.
That's pretty large given that 8 bits is how ASI
is represented in Undeode is 32 bits. But the idea
is is there's a lot of characters sets around this
universe. Now, we're not inventing too many more
and they did things like added emojis to Unicode,
but basically 32 bits is like in the billions of
possible characters. So, I think we're probably
okay. The problem is is as we move between
computers or store data on hard drives, we don't
really want every character to take up 32 bits.
So for example, Python 3 internally represents
strings as Unicode, which means they're pretty
large. Okay? But then before we stick them on
a hard drive or send them across a network,
we condense them. And there are ways to compress
these 32-bit unic codes into shorter. So one is
UTF-32 which is four byte stuff. That's the long
one. It's fixed length and it just says we'll
take that whole unic code and send it along.
UTF-16 is fixed length. It's two bytes. It's a
lot denser and um there's a mapping. Um but the
most successful one of these is a thing called
UTF8 which might not be intuitive but basically
UTF8 is one to four bytes and it is for most ASI
UTF8 and ASI are the same things and then there's
these little extension codes I mean this is a 16-
bit code or a 32-bit code and so you can represent
all of Unicode with UTF8 sometimes you're sending
one bite if it's ASKY, sometimes two, three,
and even four bytes are being sent across. And
so UTF8 is pretty much the practice for encoding
data to be exchanged across systems. So I got to
have a graph here that sort of shows that, you
know, in 2008 there was choices to be made. Um,
but since then everything is pretty much UTF8. And
so we're at the point now where systems that are
reading and writing data to disk or the network
only pretty much use UTF8. And it happens to be
ASKY. That works. Okay. But what we're doing
is we're working on a computer from the 1970s,
which is this 6502 computer. And so we're going
to just accept that it's ASI for now. But real
computers tend to work in UTF8 and can convert
from ASI or Unicode to UTF8 uh quite nicely.
[Music] [Applause] [Music]